<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY key="dmimggrad" context="tools" refkeywords="dm image images edge gradient laplace roberts prewitt sobel robison kirsch" seealsogroups="dmimgtools">
<SYNOPSIS>
  Computes the gradients of an image   
</SYNOPSIS>
<SYNTAX>
<LINE>
   dmimggrad infile outfile gradient value [verbose] [clobber]
</LINE>

</SYNTAX>
<ADDRESS><URL>dmimggrad.html</URL></ADDRESS>
<ADDRESS>
<URL>http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/dmimggrad.html</URL>

</ADDRESS>
<DESC>
<PARA>
  `dmimggrad' computes one of serveral gradient estimators of the input image.
These gradients are useful as edge detectors in the input images.  The output
image can be the gradient along either image axis (x or y), the magnitude of
the gradient (sqrt((x^2)+(y^2))), or the angle of the gradient (atan2(y,x)).
</PARA>
<LIST>
 <CAPTION>Gradient Estimators</CAPTION>
  <ITEM> Laplace - The Laplace operator is not sensitive to rotation 
(so X and Y) are the same.  There are several varients of this operator.  The 
one dmimggrad uses is ((0,1,0),(1,-4,1),(0,1,0)).  Since this operator is 
rotation invarient, the angle values are all identically 0.</ITEM>
  <ITEM> Roberts - The Roberts operator uses a small convolution kernel and is
marginally faster than the other operators; however, it is also more
suspectable to noise.  The kernels (not quite x- and y-, but interpreted as
such) are x=((1,0),(0,-1)) and y=((0,1),(-1,0))</ITEM>
  <ITEM> Prewitt - The Prewitt operator can give directional info about the 
angle of the gradient.  The kernels are x=((1,1,1),(0,0,0),(-1,-1,-1)) and
y=((-1,-1,-1),(0,0,0),(1,1,1))</ITEM>
  <ITEM> Sobel - The Sobel kernels are x=((1,2,1),(0,0,0),(-1,-2,-1)) and
y=((-1,0,1),(-2,0,2),(-1,0,1)).  It ephases data in the same row more than
the Prewitt.</ITEM>
  <ITEM> Robinson - The kernels are x=((1,1,1),(1,-2,1),(-1,-1,-1)) and
y=((-1,1,1),(-1,-2,1),(-1,1,1)) </ITEM>
  <ITEM> Kirsch - The kernels are x=((3,3,3),(3,0,3),(-5,-5,-5)) and
y=((-5,3,3),(-5,0,3),(-5,3,3)) </ITEM>

</LIST>

<PARA>
  The output image can be either the gradient along the X-direction,
along the Y-direction, the magnitude of the gradient, or the angle of the 
gradient.
</PARA>

<PARA>
  dmimggrad will respect the NULL or NaN values in the input image
(the values are skipped an the mask is effectively reduced); similarly any
image subspace (region filter) is respected.  Edges are clipped so that the 
mask is again reduced in size.
</PARA>
<PARA>
  Note:  These kernels are NOT energy preserving.  
</PARA>
</DESC>
<QEXAMPLELIST>
<QEXAMPLE>
  <SYNTAX>
    <LINE>
  dmimggrad smoothed.fits mag.fits laplace mag
    </LINE>
  </SYNTAX>
  <DESC>
    <PARA>
  Compute the Laplace gradient operator and output the magnitude
  of the gradient.  As suggested by the infile name, pre-smoothing
  images typically reduces noise and made finding edges easier.     
    </PARA>
  </DESC>
</QEXAMPLE>

<QEXAMPLE>
  <SYNTAX>
    <LINE>
    dmimggrad smoothed.fits xgrad.fits sobel x
    </LINE>
   </SYNTAX>
  <DESC>
    <PARA>
    Computes the Sobel gradient estimator in the X-direction.
    </PARA>
  </DESC>
</QEXAMPLE>



</QEXAMPLELIST>
<PARAMLIST>
<PARAM name="infile" type="file" reqd="yes" filetype="input">
<SYNOPSIS>

	The input image.
    
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

  The input 2D image.  
      
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="outfile" type="file" reqd="yes" filetype="output">
<SYNOPSIS>

	The output file name
    
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>
   The output gradient image.
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="gradient" type="string" reqd="yes" def="laplace">
<SYNOPSIS>

  Gradient operator
    
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

  The gradient estimator to use.  The available options are
  laplace, roberts, prewitt, sobel, robison, and kirsch.

</PARA>
</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="value" type="string" reqd="yes" def="mag" >
<SYNOPSIS>
  What values to output
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
  <PARA>
  What values are to be computed for the output image. Valid
  option are x (gradient in X-direction), y (gradient in the Y-direction),
  mag (magnitude of gradient) and angle (angle of gradient)

  </PARA>
</DESC>
</PARAM>

<PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
<SYNOPSIS>

	Remove output if it exists?
    
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

	Used to specify whether or not to clobber existing file that
	has the same name as the specified output file
         
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="0" min="0" max="5">
<SYNOPSIS>

	The tool chatter level
    
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

	Verbose can be from 0 to 5, generating different amounts
        of debugging output.
         
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
</PARAMLIST>
<BUGS><PARA>
	See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/dmimggrad.html">bugs page
	for this tool</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA></BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 3.0</VERSION>
<LASTMODIFIED>June 2003</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY>

</cxchelptopics>
